(upbeat music)
- Hello English learners,
welcome back to English POD.
My name is Marco.
- And I'm Erica.
- And today we're bringing you
another lesson on our Sports series.
- We're talking about baseball today.
- Baseball, the American national pastime.
- Is it?
- Yes, it is.
- Okay.
- So we're gonna be looking
at this interesting sport
that is played mainly in
the Caribbean and well, it's
actually very popular in
the United States and Japan.
- That's right.
- Korea.
- Yep.
We're only gonna learn a
bunch of baseball language,
but we're also going to see how baseball
has a big influence on English in general.
- That's right.
So we're gonna learn a
lot of great things today.
So why don't we start
and listen to our dialogue.
(upbeat music)
- Hello baseball fans and
welcome back to today's game.
My name is Rick Field
and of course I am here
once again with the man that
seals the deal, Bob Copeland.
It's a beautiful day to
see two world-class teams
face each other and fight for
their right to be called champions.
- Well, the national anthem has just been
sung and the umpire has started the game.
It's time to play ball.
Roger Vergus is up at bat.
Picture winds up and strike one.
Very nice curve ball by the pitcher.
The catcher gives him
the sign, he winds up,
and Vergus gets a line drive.
The players are scrambling to get the ball.
Vergus gets to first base
and he's still doing it.
The outfielder throws it to second.
Vergus slides, he's safe, great play.
We have a runner on third
and up at bat is Brian O'Cami.
There's the pitch, he hits it.
It's going, going, that ball is gone.
Home run by O'Cami.
That puts this team ahead
by two as we are at the
bottom of the fifth inning
here at Richie Stadium.
(crowd cheering)
(upbeat music)
All right, well, a pretty exciting
game there at Richie Stadium.
- Exactly, and we have some interesting
players, Roger Vergus and Brian O'Cami.
- Mm-hmm.
- All right, so, well, we
saw some great words
and well, it's time for us to take a
look at them now in language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
- Okay, we're gonna look at some
common sports and baseball words here.
Now, the first phrase will hear this
almost at any sort of
international sports event, right?
- Exactly, and it's the national anthem.
- National anthem.
- So, this is a song, right?
- Exactly, it's the song
that you sing about
your country and many
people confuse it, right?
- Yeah, a lot of people
might say national hymn.
- Okay, hymn.
- Because in some languages,
it might be like a hymn,
like literally translating, but in
English, it's called the national anthem.
- The national anthem.
- All right, so what about our next word?
- Well, we were talking about the pitcher.
- Pitcher, P-I-T-C-H-E-R,
the pitcher, pitcher.
- Okay, and now this is one of the players
on the baseball team and his job is to...
- To throw the ball.
- To throw the ball really fast.
So that the guy can
hit it with the bat, okay.
So that's the pitcher.
Now, the interesting thing is
that the baseball commentator
said the pitcher winds up,
winds up, to wind up, to wind up.
Okay, well, let me paint you a picture.
- Okay.
- So imagine a clock,
and you're turning, turning,
and turning the clock to
wind up to get it ready to go.
- To make it work.
- Exactly.
- So imagine the pitcher
doing the same sort of thing,
bringing his arm back behind
him, getting ready to throw the ball.
- Okay, so that is to wind up.
Very good.
So you can use this
word not only in baseball,
but for other things that
require you to do the section.
- Right, to turn something and
get it ready to have lots of power.
- Like some toys, or
maybe like a music box.
Okay, wind up.
What about our next phrase?
- Well, Roger Vargas hit a line drive.
- Line drive.
- Okay, so what is a line drive?
- What's a term from baseball?
And when you hit a line drive, you hit the
ball, sort of low, on towards the ground,
and it travels along
the outside of the field.
- Right, so the ball basically
travels along the foul line.
- That white line.
- The white line.
- Yeah, exactly.
Very good, so that's a line drive.
- And so the players on the field
were scrambling to get the ball.
- Scrambling. - Scrambling.
Now, we know scrambled
eggs from one of our lessons.
- Yes, but the verb "to
scramble" means to move quickly
in a disorganized way to do something.
- Okay, so the players
are moving very fast,
trying to get the ball, but
they're not doing it very well.
- Right, and you can use
this in other ways, right?
Not just in baseball.
- Right, for example, we can say the people
are scrambling to buy
their tickets for the concert.
- Yeah, or I'm going on vacation tomorrow
and I'm scrambling to get everything ready.
- Exactly.
It's a very good term that you
can use also in your daily life.
- Exactly.
All right, and what about our last
word for today on language takeaway?
- Well, they were in the
fifth inning of the game.
- Okay, so inning, inning, inning.
- All right, this is another baseball
term, and it just means the period of play.
- Okay, so we learned, for
example, that in soccer you
have two halves, or in
hockey you have three periods.
- All right.
- And in baseball you have nine innings.
- Okay, great, so some interesting
sports and baseball vocabulary.
Now, I think it'll help us
to hear this again slower.
So let's listen to the dialogue.
(upbeat music)
- Hello baseball fans, and
welcome back to today's game.
My name is Rick Fields,
and of course, I am here once
again with the man that
seals the deal, Bob Copeland.
It's a beautiful day to
see two world-class teams
face each other and fight for
their right to be called champions.
Well, the national anthem has just been
sung, and the umpire has started the game.
It's time to play ball.
Roger Vargas is up at bat.
The pitcher winds up, and strike one.
A very nice curve ball by the pitcher.
The catcher gives him
the sign, he winds up,
and Vargas gets a line drive.
The players are scrambling to get the ball.
Vargas gets to first
base, and he's still going.
The outfielder throws it to second.
Vargas slides, he's safe, great play.
We have a runner on third,
and up at bat is Brian O'Cami.
There's the pitch, he hits it.
It's going, going, that ball is gone.
Home run by O'Cami.
That puts this team ahead
by two, as we are at the
bottom of the fifth inning
here at Ritchie Stadium.
(upbeat music)
All right, so as we said, there are a lot
of English terms that come from baseball,
but we use them in business
context or in your daily life, right?
Yeah, why don't we look at
those now in Fluency Builder?
Fluency Builder.
All right, so the first phrase
that we have is up to bat.
Up to bat, up to bat.
So literally in this
dialogue, it means the guy is
standing on home plate
ready to hit the ball, right?
He has the bat and he's ready to hit it.
But what about in other contexts?
So for example, you can be at a meeting,
and maybe it's your turn to talk.
So you're up to bat.
So exactly, your boss will say,
okay, Erica, you're up to bat.
Okay, so it means sort
of like it's your turn.
It's your turn.
Very good.
All right, so that's another
term that is using baseball,
but very commonly used
in other circumstances.
So we also saw in the
dialogue that Roger Vegas,
he hit the ball, but he
missed and that was strike one.
Right, strike one.
So in baseball, you have three strikes.
Three tries.
Three tries before you're out.
Yes.
And so now the same
thing happens in daily life.
So if someone says that was strike
one, it means you made the first mistake.
Yes.
And if you make two more,
you will be fired for example.
Yeah. Or maybe your parents will
say, okay, that wasn't nice, strike one.
And then two more times
and you'll have a timeout.
Oh, you'll be grounded.
Yes.
Okay, so that's also called a strike.
And the picture through a curve ball.
A curve ball.
Curve ball.
So, okay, pretty clear.
A curve ball is when you throw
the ball and it sort of goes in a curve.
It doesn't go straight, right?
Right, exactly.
But how can this be
used outside of baseball?
So you can say, oh, my boss
threw me a curve ball today.
So he gave you an unexpected problem.
Or something that was difficult to handle.
Okay, this one is pretty interesting.
I'd like to hear a few more examples.
Example one.
My boss threw me a curve ball today.
So I have to stay and work late.
Example two.
It was a huge curve ball when she
asked me how many kids I wanted to have.
How am I supposed to know?
All right, so that's
basically a curve ball.
You can say an unexpected
problem or situation.
That's right.
And our last phrase and we'll probably
one that you already know, home run.
A home run.
From baseball, we know that
that's when you hit the ball really far.
And you hit it outside of the
playing area, outside the park.
Yes.
And now if you use it in a business context
or in your daily life, it
means something similar.
Why don't we take a listen to the
examples and see if we can figure it out.
Example one.
Great job on that sales presentation.
You really hit a home run.
Example two.
Our sales team hit a home run
this month by doubling our revenue.
Okay, so basically a home run is a success.
A victory.
Yeah, something, a big accomplishment.
That's right.
So we've seen a lot of these great phrases.
And as you can see, a lot of them
from baseball are using your daily life.
And there are many, many more.
Okay, well, why don't we hear
them again in the baseball context
and we'll listen to the
dialogue one more time.
(upbeat music)
- Hello baseball fans.
And welcome back to today's game.
My name is Rick Field.
And of course I am here once again with
the man that seals the deal, Bob Copeland.
It's a beautiful day to
see two world class teams
face each other and fight for
their right to be called champions.
Well, the National Anthem has just been
sung and the Empire has started the game.
It's time to play ball.
Roger Vergus is up at bat.
Picture winds up and strike one.
Very nice curve ball by the pitcher.
The catcher gives him the sign.
He winds up and Vargas gets a line drive.
The players are scrambling to get the ball.
Vargas gets to first base
and he's still doing it.
The outfielder throws it to second.
Vergus slides, he's safe, great play.
We have a runner on third
and up at bat is Brian O'Cami.
There's the pitch, he hits it.
It's going, going, that ball is gone.
Home run by O'Cami.
That puts this team ahead
by two as we are at the
bottom of the fifth inning
here at Richie Stadium.
(upbeat music)
- All right, so an interesting dialogue
is a very interesting sport and well,
personally, I never played this as a child.
I mean, either, really.
I don't really like it too much,
but it is kind of fun to go to a game
and especially in the United States
have those hot dogs and all that.
- Okay, yep.
- Well, a cultural event.
A really important
piece of American culture.
- Exactly.
So, well, we encourage you to
come to our website, englishpot.
com.
Tell us what you think and also, of course,
if you have questions or
doubts, be sure to tell us.
If you have any other
sort of baseball related
phrases, let us know
about them on the website.
- Okay, so we'll see you guys there.
- Thanks for downloading,
and until next time, goodbye.
- Bye.
(upbeat music)